{"tossups": [{"question": "The remnants of this government established the Republic of Ezo after losing the Boshin War. Two and a half centuries earlier, this government was founded after its leader won the Battle of Sekigahara against the Toyotomi clan. This government\u2019s policy of sakoku came to an end when Matthew Perry\u2019s Black Ships forced the opening of Japan through the 1854 Convention of Kanagawa. For ten points, name this last Japanese shogunate.", "answer": "<b> Tokugawa</b> Shogunate (or<b> Tokugawa</b> Bakufu)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "enophon\u2019s<em> Anabasis</em> describes ten thousand Greek soldiers of this type who fought Artaxerxes II of Persia. A war named for these people was won by Hamilcar Barca and led to his conquest of Spain. Famed soldiers of this type include slingers from Rhodes and archers from Crete. Greeks who fought for Persia were, for ten points, what type of soldier that fought not for national pride, but for money?", "answer": "<b> mercenary</b> (prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Joseph Bazalgette designed this city\u2019s sewer system, which reduced the frequency of cholera outbreaks and prevented a recurrence of the 1858 \u201cGreat Stink.\u201d This city was one of first sites for rubber to be grown outside of South America, as part of a botanical research project at Kew. This city\u2019s Crystal Palace stood in its Hyde Park until 1936 and was opened in 1851 by Queen Victoria. Sewage was once pumped into the River Thames in, for ten points, what capital city of England?", "answer": "<b> London</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "On this island, a 5th century BC law code inscribed on circular walls can be seen in ruins in Gortyn. This island is home to a distinctive type of pottery known as the \u201ckamares ware,\u201d examples of which are on display in Heraklion. The Thera volcanic eruption may have ended a civilization on this island, where frescos depicting a bull-leaping motif are common at the palace of Knossos. For ten points, name this largest Greek island, the center of the Minoan civilization.", "answer": "<b> Crete</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A former Speaker of this state\u2019s House of Representatives ran for the Senate in 2010, beating Kendrick Meek and Charlie Crist. A Congresswoman from this state resigned as DNC chair after a scandal involving Wikileaks and her hacked emails. Rick Scott governs, for ten points, what swing state that was represented by Debbie Wasserman Schultz in the House and is currently represented in the Senate by Marco Rubio?", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Anna Chennault arranged a meeting for this man with Ambassador Bui Diem that violated the Logan Act. Charles Colson admitted this man had told him that a typewriter was fabricated in the Alger Hiss case. This politician sabotaged peace talks in Vietnam in the aforementioned Chennault affair, promising better results after this man defeated Hubert Humphrey in the 1968 election. For ten points, name this US President who withdrew the US from Vietnam in 1973.", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Domus Conversorum was a residence specifically built to house these people, many of whom died when Clifford\u2019s Tower, the keep of York Castle, was burned to the ground in 1190. Oliver Cromwell ended a policy whereby these people had been banned from England since the reign of Edward I. The Balfour Declaration pledged support for the creation of a homeland for these people in the Middle East. For ten points, name this religious group whose British members have included Benjamin Disraeli.", "answer": "<b> Jew</b>ish people", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a novel set in this country, Aurora de Gama falls in love with the manager at her father\u2019s spice warehouse; that novel takes its name from the dying reaction of Boabdil and is titled<em> The Moor\u2019s Last</em> <em>Sigh</em>. A group of telepathic youths hold a conference in this country in a novel in which Saleem Sinai was born at the exact moment of this country\u2019s independence. For ten points, name this setting of Salman Rushdie\u2019s novel<em> Midnight\u2019s Children</em>.", "answer": "<b> India</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "In his early military career, this man was given the honor of escorting the captured chief Black Hawk. Officials picked for this man\u2019s Cabinet included Stephen Mallory and Judah Benjamin. His vice president, Alexander Stephens, stated that this man\u2019s government was founded \u201cupon the great truth\u201d of racial inequality. Command of the Army of Northern Virginia was given to Robert E. Lee by, for ten points, what only president of the Confederate States of America?", "answer": "Jefferson<b> Davis</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s<em> mothax</em> were allowed to fight, but denied the right to join in communal banquets where a black broth was served. Every autumn in this city, the<em> krypteia</em> were permitted to slaughter slaves to prevent events like the Messenian Wars and other helot uprisings. This city\u2019s<em> agoge</em> [uh-goh-gay] system trained boys from the age of 7 into this city\u2019s elite military. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state whose army fought Athens in the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b> Sparta</b> (or<b> Lacedaemon</b>ia)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1341, a holder of this title instituted a salt tax called the gabelle. This title was promised to Henry V at the Treaty of Troyes and was split from the Kingdom of Navarre by Joan II. The next holder of this position was known as the dauphin. After 987, holders of this position were descended from Hugh Capet. For ten points, name this royal title held by eighteen different men with regnal name Louis.", "answer": "<b> King of France</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cking\u201d or \u201cmonarch of France;\u201d accept <b>Queen of France</b> before \u201cHenry V\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Demilitarization along this border was planned by the Rush-Bagot Treaty. Confusion over this border led to a bloodless war after a pig was shot on San Juan Island. Lumberjack infighting along this border led to the Aroostook War, which was ended by a treaty negotiated by Daniel Webster. This border was initially demarcated by the 1783 Treaty of Paris following the American Revolution. For ten points, name this border whose eastern end lies between Maine and New Brunswick.", "answer": "the border between<b> Canada</b> and the<b> United States</b> of America (accept<b> US</b>A or<b> America </b>for United States; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Clausius\u2019 inequality was an early formulation of a law concerning this quantity, whose public awareness grew through Isaac Asimov\u2019s short story \u201cThe Last Question.\u201d Early theories on this quantity were developed by Lazare Carnot [la-zarr car-noh], whose namesake cycle conserves this quantity. Ludwig Boltzmann\u2019s tombstone has an equation for this quantity engraved on it. According to the second law of thermodynamics, this quantity always increases within isolated systems. For ten points, name this measure of disorder within a system.", "answer": "<b> entropy</b> (prompt on S)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This writer became President of Czechoslovakia in 1989.", "answer": "V\u00b4aclav<b> Havel</b> <b></b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>In 2015, members of this group noted \u201cIt. Just. Isn\u2019t. That. Good.\u201d in their two-star review of</b><em><b> In the Aeroplane Over the Sea</b></em><b> by Neutral Milk Hotel. That review was labeled\u201cDisgusting\u201d by a website that later praised a State Department effort to counter this</b> <b>group: a world map with the US (+)</b> <b>shrunk to be too small for this group to find. In real</b> <b>life, a member of this group used the caption \u201cWe respawn in Jannah\u201d in an (*)</b> Instagram post referencing<em> Call of Duty</em>, one of its numerous recruitment attempts over social media. Clickhole.com frequently lampoons, for ten points, what terrorist group that lost control of Mosul in July 2017?", "answer": "<b> IS</b>IS (or<b> Islamic State</b> of Iraq and Syria; or<b> IS</b>IL; or<b> Islamic State</b> of Iraq and the Levant; or<b> Daesh</b>; accept descriptions of Clickhole.com\u2019s version of <b>IS</b>IS; prompt on Clickhole before mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This organization used a sacred messenger vehicle called the</b><em><b> Paralus</b></em><b>. This organization,</b> <b>which was wiped out after the Battle of Aegospotami, was based at (+)</b> <b>Piraeus, a city</b> <b>guarded by the Long Walls. This organization withdrew from the Battle of Cape Artemisium and later won the decisive Battle of (*) </b> Salamis, driving the Persians from Greece. Themistocles advocated for the expansion of, for ten points, what military force whose triremes ensured the Delian League\u2019s control of the Aegean Sea?", "answer": "<b> navy</b> of ancient<b> Athens</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cAthens\u2019 military\u201d or \u201c(Greek) navy;\u201d do not accept or prompt on answers like \u201cAthens\u2019 army\u201d or \u201cthe modern Greek navy\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The memorial site of Castle Hill in this region is sometimes named after Alexander Baranov, who established a provisional capital here in the early 1800s after defeating Tlingit</b> <b>natives. This region\u2019s ports of (+)</b> <b>Dyea and Skagway boomed in the 1890s as through</b> <b>points for gold prospectors. Sitka was the (*)</b> Russian territorial capital of this region, which was acquired by the U.S. in 1867 in a move dubbed Seward\u2019s Folly. For ten points, name this modern US state home to the cities of Fairbanks and Anchorage.", "answer": "<b> Alaska</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Planes intercepted over this facility are often forced to land in nearby Hagerstown. This facility is officially designated NSF Thurmont and was known as \u201cShangri-La\u201d in the (+) </b> <b>1940s. In 1978, this facility hosted meetings that created two frameworks: the first was condemned by the UN, but the second earned (*) </b> Menachim Began and Anwar Sadat a shared Nobel Prize. For ten points, name this Maryland facility, a Presidential retreat where Jimmy Carter hosted Middle East peace talks that produced a set of Accords.", "answer": "<b> Camp David</b> (accept<b> N</b>aval<b> S</b>upport<b> F</b>acility<b> Thurmont</b> before mentioned; accept<b> Shangri-La</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A speech advocating for this action was given \u201cat a college noted for knowledge, in a city noted for progress, in a state noted for strength.\u201d This action was compared to \u201cclimb[ing]</b> <b>the highest mountain,\u201d \u201cfly[ing] the Atlantic,\u201d and (+)</b> <b>\u201cRice play[ing] Texas\u201d in a 1962</b> <b>speech that noted \u201cwe choose to\u201d do this \u201cin this decade.\u201d The development of the (*) </b>Saturn V [five] propulsion system was instrumental in performing this action, which was last done by the<em> Challenger</em> lander in 1972. For ten points, name this exploration first done by Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong aboard<em> Apollo 11</em>.", "answer": "<b> going to the Moon</b> (accept equivalents related to a manned<b> Moon landing</b>; accept any additional information related to John F. Kennedy\u2019s push for Americans/NASA<b> going to the moon</b>; prompt on \u201cthe Apollo program,\u201d \u201cApollo 11,\u201d \u201cfunding NASA,\u201d and other similar answers that don\u2019t mention the specific goal of a moon landing)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>After natives in what is now this country committed a ritual mass suicide known as </b><em><b>puputan</b></em><b>, the city of Klungkung fell to European colonists. A ruler of this country established a system called USDEK to implement (+) Guided Democracy; that system fell apart after the 30 September Movement and gave way to the New Order. Mohammad Hatta served as Vice President and Prime Minister for the (*) </b> INP in, for ten points, what Asian country, once led by Sukarno and Suharto, whose capital is Jakarta?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Indonesia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}